Guide to the Edward Gordon Craig Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edward Gordon Craig collection
1905-1963
GEN MSS 433
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.05
(4 boxes) + 2 portfolios
Craig, Edward Gordon, 1872-1966
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Portfolio folders 31-34: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
EDWARD GORDON CRAIG, 1872-1966
Edward Gordon Craig was born in England on 16 January 1872, the son of the actress Ellen Terry and the architect E. W. (Edward William) Godwin. In 1878, at the age of six, he made his first stage appearance in a production of Olivia, by W. G. Wills. He studied at Southfield Park and Bradfield College, and was a member of Henry Irving's theater company at the Lyceum Theatre in London beginning in 1889.
In 1893, Craig married May Gibson, and moved from London to Uxbridge. Under the influence of the artists James Ferrier Pryde and William Nicholson, he learned the art of wood-engraving, and began his career as a graphic designer. In 1893 he directed and designed his first stage production: Alfred de Musset's On ne badine pas avec l'amour. Around this time he also published a magazine, The Page, consisting mostly of his own engravings, and in 1899 published a book of woodcuts with accompanying verses entitled Gordon Craig's Book of Penny Toys.
Craig's career as a stage designer continued to evolve as he collaborated with Martin Shaw in 1901 and 1902 productions of Dido and Aeneas, The Mask of Love and other plays. In 1904 Craig traveled to Berlin to work with the Lessing Theatre, and in 1905 he published his most famous essay, The Art of the Theatre, which was later expanded and republished as On the Art of the Theatre. In Germany he met the dancer Isadora Duncan, with whom he had a brief but intense affair, ending in 1906. Duncan persuaded the theater producer Konstantin Stanislavsky to invite Craig to Moscow, and there he designed an important 1912 production of Hamlet. In 1913, Craig fulfilled a longtime dream by founding his School for the Art of the Theatre in the Arena Goldoni in Florence; however, it closed shortly thereafter at the outbreak of World War I.
Over his long career Craig became known as an important innovator in theater design, popularizing a modern, minimalist style in contrast to the more extravagant style of his mother's age, and his writings, artwork and design had an enormous impact on twentieth-century theater. His publications include the theatrical periodical The Mask (1908-1929), and the books Books and Theatres (1925), Ellen Terry and Her Secret Self (1931), Nothing, or, the Bookplate (1924), The Theatre - Advancing (1919) and his autobiography, Index to the Story of My Days (1957). He spent the last years of his life in the south of France, and died there in 1966.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Edward Gordon Craig, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Series I, Hamill and Barker Purchase (1912-1958), contains letters from a variety of correspondents to Craig's friend Ewald Junge, who also collected Craig material. The letters include five folders of letters from Craig, and notes on Craig's collection of his own personal papers. Series II, Materials from Other Sources (1905-1963), includes an annotated copy of Craig's autobiography, Index to the Story of My Days, with clippings, photographs and proofs of woodcuts laid in, and letters, notes and a specimen page removed from the volume and foldered; one letter from Craig to Theodore Sizer accompanied by a small etching; two woodcuts by Craig inscribed to Haldane and Mabel Macfall; forty photographs relating to Craig's scenic models for the 1912 Moscow Art Theatre production of Hamlet; and prospectus, dummy, first proof and revised proof with corrections of Craig's book Towards a New Theatre.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Hamill and Barker Purchase, 1912-1958. II. Materials from Other Sources, 1905-1963.
Set designers; Theater -- Production and direction; Theaters -- Stage-setting and scenery; Etchings (prints); Photographs; Woodcuts (prints); Set designers; Craig, Edward Gordon, 1872-1966; Craig, Edward Gordon, 1872-1966 ( Towards a new theatre); Junge, Ewald; Macfall, Haldane, 1860-1928; Macfall, Mabel; Moskovskiĭ khudozhestvennyĭ akademicheskiĭ teatr
- Hamill and Barker Purchase, 1912-1958; Series I; 0.3; (.75 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Purchased from Hamill and Barker on the Library Associates Fund, 1969
  - LETTERS TO EWALD JUNGE
    - British Broadcasting Corporation, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Beerbohm, Max, 1954 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - British Council, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Browne, E. Martin (Elliott Martin), 1949-56 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Craig, Edward Gordon, 1953-58 (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
      Includes: Letter to EGC from Lawrence Irving, 15 October 1957
    - Fitzgerald, Desmond, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Harling, Robert, [1948] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Heinemann (Firm), 1952 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Irving, Laurence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Nicoll, Allardyce, 1948 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Shaw, Martin, [1952 Jan 15] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Old Vic Theatre (London, England), 1948-51 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Unesco, 1947 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - University of California, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Victoria and Albert Museum, 1948-51 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Whitworth, Geoffrey, 1912-48 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - "Notes on Mr. Gordon Craig's Personal Collection at St. Germain," typescript, 1940 Jan (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Materials from Other Sources, 1905-1963; Series II; 0.5; (2.25 boxes)
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders
  - MATERIALS REMOVED FROM INDEX TO THE STORY OF MY DAYS
    - Letters to Edward Gordon Craig
      - Blair, Frederika, 1958 Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Hoover, Gene Boardman, 1958 Jan 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Hulton Press Ltd, 1955, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Other Papers
      - Notes and clippings, 1905-63, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Specimen page for "Gordon Craig's Memoirs", 1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - OTHER MATERIALS
    - ALS from EGC to Theodore Sizer, 1924 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Includes: Penny etching by EGC, 1922
    - Index to the Story of My Days, printed volume, Hulton Press, London, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Includes: Extensive annotations by EGC, clippings, proofs of woodcuts, photographs of EGC (1905), Dixton Manor House (n.d.), and the Theatre Royal (1954)
    - Woodcut entitled "Hunger", 1908 (Box port, Folder 29)
      Inscribed to Haldane Macfall and Mabel Macfall
    - Woodcut of a skeleton, 1925 (Box port, Folder 30)
      Inscribed to Haldane Macfall
    - Black-and-white photographs made by Craig of his scenic models for the Stanislavsky and Craig production of Hamlet at the Moscow Art Theatre (1912), [1909-11],undated (Box 3, Folder 35-39)
      Includes: Photograph of Craig with scenic model in his garden; two photographs of an actor in costume for Hamlet and one of a staff member standing beside a scenic model; and two photographs of Craig's office.
    - Prospectus, dummy, first proof and revised proof with corrections of Towards a New Theatre; with typed letter, signed, dated 1913 February 13, from Dent & Sons, Publisher, to Craig regarding proofs., 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 40-45)
- Restricted Fragile, (1 portfolio)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 7 (Box port, Folder 31)
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box port, Folder 32)
  - Box 1, folder 20 (Box port, Folder 33)
  - Box 1, folder 25 (Box port, Folder 34)